hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of holotalk
for the week of July 2nd 2000 our
special guest this week is Gloria Putnam
from women in Optics with spie and she's
going to be coming on telling us a
little bit about that organization and
their objectives and also give us a look
into the Optics industry itself and
where it is right now and where it's
headed in the future if we don't wind up
getting more students interested in
pursuing this field as a career I also
want to call your attention if you
happen to be an educator to a download
that I have on the page and that will
download a Microsoft Word document to
your computer which you can review and
that is for the Optics educator Network
and if you would be interested in
getting your students involved with
Optics in the classroom they have a
number of different benefits available
to you for doing that and it's a free
membership as well to become part of
that Network so if you're an educator
take a look at that download that and
contact Gloria as to whether you'd be
interested in that further or not
before we get started with Gloria I have
an announcement to make that was sent to
me from Dan Schweitzer and Dan wanted
everyone to know that the center for the
holographic Arts is extending their
deadline for their Artisan Residency
program until August 15th of 2000 if you
happen to be a holographer or even a
non-holographer if you're an artist and
you'd like to go into the lab and do
some work you're invited to submit a
proposal and you now have until August
15 2000 to do so it's a great program
it's a great facility Michelle Roy and I
visited there and we have a number of
programs from the center for the
holographic arts on the archive page for
holotalk and it's a wonderful facility
it's a great opportunity for anyone who
would want to work in the field of
holography and produce some holographic
work so even if you applied before you
might want to resubmit your proposal
once again and once again you all you
have until August 15th to do that
okay here's the interview with Gloria
first I would like to point out that I
also have a link to the women in Optics
website I encourage you to click on that
link and go visit and see what they're
about directly from the website and I
also have an email link for Gloria which
will send her an email if you happen to
would if you would like to have
additional information about the group
itself and she's also located on the
women in Optics website itself with her
email address and once again if you
happen to be an educator don't forget
about the download for the educator
Network download it and review it and
see what you think
all right so I'm going to say thank you
for tuning in I'm not going to come back
on after the program's over and I'd like
to invite you to tune in it won't be
each week during the summer as you know
usually I would go off the air during
the summer for the past three years I've
done that but I received a number of
emails saying that listeners would like
to have shows over the summer so
occasionally we're going to be coming on
with new topics and new guests
throughout the summer and then we'll be
going into our fourth season Labor Day
which we will be back on the air every
week with a new guests in a new topic so
thank you very much for tuning in and
talk to you next time here's Gloria
hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
welcome to another week of whole talk
and we have a special guest this week
Gloria Putnam and you're on to talk
about the working group which is women
and Optics and and I know we've just
spent about 45 minutes on the phone I'm
going to have to ask you to go over a
few things again but why don't you just
start off by letting the listeners know
a little bit about the group and what
the focus of the group is
sure women and Optics is like you say a
working group that was formed within
spie but certainly membership in the
group is open to anyone whether they're
an spie member or not and the group has
existed for a couple of years now and
the main the main goals of the group are
to raise the visibility of women working
in the field because our numbers are
very low and
the reason that we want to do that of
course is is is to
to give to provide role models for for
younger Engineers who may be considering
careers and Optics who are women or for
younger students who maybe wouldn't
think of themselves in this type of
career unless they see
um someone else doing someone else doing
it yeah who looks like someone that they
could be
and we a lot of our efforts are also
directed at providing kind of a unique
networking atmosphere for women in the
field so you take a cross-section of the
field that's all women and you end up
with women from all types of sectors of
the photonics industry and so networking
within the group is really interesting
because you get to learn about things at
all different types of people are doing
we have meetings twice a year we meet at
photonics West and at the annual meeting
these are both spie meetings and at
those meetings we have speakers and
we've got a meeting coming up actually
because I can give you the information
sure at the spie annual meeting in San
Diego on August 3rd we're having a
meeting it's from 5 30 to 7 30 p.m in
the the main conference hotel which I
believe is the Marriott down there and
we're going to kind of do an update of
what's going on with the working group
and we have a really great speaker plan
it's Dr Gabriella with us Sue and I'm
not sure I'm saying her name correctly
but she's
Technologies Optical networking and
she's going to talk a little bit about
Optical networking enablers to give us
an overview of that field and talk a
little bit about her work in that hot
and booming area so it's not going to
dinners following all of our meetings
and also at meetings where we don't have
real women and Optics meetings we
usually try to organize dinners informal
dinners yeah for members and that's also
part of what we do now you mentioned
about hot and booming field and during
our earlier conversation you spoke a
little bit about a conference that you
attended where you received some actual
figures about what this field is like
how many people are moving into it and
what a shortage there's going to be
could you share that with the listeners
yeah yeah it's almost a national
emergency or the Optics industry really
for the whole country it it looks like
there are sectors of the Optics and
photonics Industry that are currently
their growth is limited by the lack of
Human Resources so the shortage of human
resources and at this conference there
were representatives from the human
resources department of coherent and
E-Tech talking about how difficult it is
for them to find both technicians and
engineers and researchers and the
efforts that they go to to steal workers
from each other and this is you know
raising wages and salaries and in the
end we'll make the United States
uncompetitive in these critical sectors
of technology
so we need to provide the people and
there was an interesting study done
there was a there was a White House
report released in April where they took
the makeup of the current
not really the engineering Workforce but
they looked at degrees awarded in
engineering and Science and how many of
them go to women how many go to men and
then how many go to men and all these
different
ethnicity categories and women and all
those categories and they they said
let's see what would happen if these
categories if people continue to
participate in the same percentages that
they do now and now we go 50 years in
the future and we use what we know about
what the population the makeup of the
United States population is going to
look like in 50 years
and we can involve those data sets and
what they found was that if the makeup
of these
degree granting programs doesn't change
that we're actually going to be
graduating 9 percent
wow in science and engineering in the
year 2050 than we are now now this is
obviously a problem because we're
probably going to need to be graduating
twice as many people yeah
we want to do so the main conclusion of
the report is that we really need to
we really need to address the problem of
people who are underrepresented in
engineering and increasing their
participation because that's the only
way we're going to be able to meet the
needs of Industry I imagine there's a
problem
I would imagine that the employers are
actually bringing people in from
overseas to fill a lot of these
positions that our own students right
here in the United States could be
filling
well current we are bringing a lot of
people in from overseas and there's a
program called the H-1B visa program
which allows allows skilled workers to
come over and work for a period of six
years
currently we're not worried about them
taking jobs that our kids are are
our engineers and scientists could have
because the need is still so much
greater than the number of people that
are coming in on these H-1B visas that's
not it's not limiting the job market for
a graduate and actually that the
industry is pushing really hard every
year to increase the number of these
pieces that are allowed and then there's
also a huge program to try and convert
those visas into green cards or
something more permanent so that we can
keep these people here because we need
to keep them working
those those companies I was just on the
women and Optics website a little
earlier and it's it's expanded
considerably since the last time I
visited maybe you would want to tell the
listeners a little bit about what the
website is about and what you have on
there yeah sure on the website
um there's information about membership
and there's actually two things that you
can do if you're interested one is
become a member but one thing which I
believe costs 15 if you're an spie
member I believe it's free if you're a
student and I think we might have a
similar deal for Osa members the same as
for spie members and if you're not a
member of anything then it's I think
thirty dollars to join any annual are
working
group but there's also a list serve and
if you go under I think maybe it's under
programs you can anybody can sign up for
free for our list serve and don't worry
you won't get 100 messages a day it's
not that kind of list it's just where we
disseminate information about our
meetings and let you know what things
are going on so that you can participate
so anybody can sign up for that and we
have a list also on the website of all
of our programs all the women in octopus
programs some of which are programs that
we support other people's programs a
great example of that is mentornet
electronic mentoring program that comes
out of San Diego State University
and they connect
women in undergraduate and graduate
programs in science and technology to
end ustries in to to mentors and
Industry
and they do an email mentorship thing
that lasts lasts one Academic Year and
we're a financial women not because it's
a financial supporter of that and also
have a membership drive or a mentor
Drive every year at the annual meeting
to get SPID meeting attendees to sign up
to be mentors in the program and all of
our student chapters
so
young women in our student chapters can
get mentors through this program and
it's a fabulous program so there's
information about that
and a variety of other programs that
will
there's a grant program for women who
wish to return to the workforce as well
right that's right this is a new women
in Optics program
um
we were we have been approached since
since we now have this web presence and
people are poking around finding things
we've been approached by women who are
in a situation where they have taken
some time off to raise
types of things and now they want to get
back in to the workforce and they're
trained I mean they're every company's
dream right like everybody's looking so
hard for people and here's this person
who's who's trained they probably
worked in the field for a number of
years before taking the time off and
they're just not sure quite how to get
back in
networking wise and they're not sure
where the technology has gone in the
last five years or whatever since they
worked so what our grant does is it
sponsors them to come to an spie meeting
we hook them up with a with a mentor
through women in Optics who helps
introduce them to people who work in the
fields that they know stuff about
help them prepare their resume and all
that stuff and they they get to attend a
short course and they get a travel Stipe
and then pre-registration of the meeting
and all that stuff to help them get
reconnected what's the breakdown of the
Optics field now compared to male female
ratio
of people working do you know we're not
sure but we can say that SPID membership
is about eight percent women
um statistics that I've seen for
engineering as a whole in the United
States is that
mm-hmm so I would say we're pretty close
to kind of the overall engineering
members of course we're half of the
population so you can see where the
problem is yeah we're definitely
underutilized as a potential Workforce
sector
I had Doris Villa on a few weeks ago who
was a who is a holographic artist
working out of New York and she had
mentioned that the field of holography
is pretty close to 50 50 male female
split
yeah there's a similar thing in
spectroscopy I
um spoke with someone recently who was
involved with with their professional
Society the name of which I can't
remember but they've got something like
30 percent female membership in their
society and of course there's there's a
history of women being trained long ago
you know as spectroscopists
um reading the looking at the pictures
and identifying things yes
I imagine that that there's a historical
reason you know that their numbers are
larger there so we've got some catching
up to do in engineering for sure yeah
now if there were students who are
logged on right now listening to this
and we get a ton of them
what advice would you give to them if
they wanted to pursue careers in Optics
or lasers or photonics any special
things that they should be focusing on
with their schoolwork or uh
process in which they would choose a
school to go to
yeah well I'm sure they've heard it all
before be sure you stay here in math and
science right
um
actually as an undergraduate I did a
degree in mathematics as well as a
degree in physics and that has served me
very well in Optics because there is a
lot of fun math stuff you can do if you
like that
um
there are programs all over the United
States where you can get training that
will help you for a career in Optics not
all of them are called Optics programs
there are programs that actually Grant
degrees in Optical engineering at places
like the University of Arizona numbers
Manchester and a variety of other places
but there's also there are other paths
you can take a physics degree is where I
started out and that has served me very
well and a lot of people enter the field
with degrees in electrical engineering
so those are all choices yeah
now I'm going to include a link to the
women in Optics website so if you're
listening to the show right now you'll
find that link right on the holotalk
page and if you click on that if your
listeners go to contacts also they can
find information there how to contact me
if they have any questions okay and I I
can also put a direct email link right
to you on the whole talk page now
um I believe we'll have some materials
to uh
have people download I think it's an
educator Network or something that you
started up yeah there's a new program
that's not necessarily a women in Optics
program it's more an SPID program in
general but it's it's a program that
whose aim is to create a network of K-12
Educators who are interested in teaching
Optics in their classroom and it'll be
kind of an electronic community
plans and things and spie can provide
information to them
about the resources that we offer for
educators and on the spie website
there's actually a section called called
resources for educators and there are a
variety of programs that spie is
involved in to provide materials and
lesson plans and all kinds of things for
educators
so we hope to connect with Educators
through this network and it's free you
know it's free to sign up and then
you're just on our list serve and we can
get you all together and share
information and try and hook up those
teachers
will in their local community through
our members from industry who could
come in and do classroom visits or
arrange tours of local Labs so we're
looking to kind of encourage that kind
of a Grassroots collaboration between
the teachers and the local industry
that's great
it's terrific anything else you want to
add before we close out the interview no
just thank you for inviting me it's been
a pleasure oh sure
and hang on the line and I'll pick up
the phone after we're finished here and
I want to thank the whole top listeners
for tuning in and we'll get back to our
programming